Welcome to this course on compilers. My name is Alex Aiken. I'm a professor here
欢迎参加这门关于编译器的课程。我叫亚历克斯·艾肯。我是这里的教授
at Stanford University. And we're going to be talking about the implementation of
在斯坦福大学。我们要讨论的是如何实施
programming languages. >> There are two major approaches to implementing
编程语言。>>主要有两种实现方式
programming languages, compilers, and interpreters. Now, this class is mostly
编程语言、编译器和解释器。现在，这门课主要是
about compilers. But, I do want to say a few words about interpreters here in the
关于编译器。但是，我确实想在这里说几句关于口译员的事情。
first lecture. So, what does an interpreter do? Well, I'm gonna draw a
第一堂课。那么，口译员是做什么的呢？好的，我要画一个
picture here, this box is the interpreter, and it takes, let me label it with a big
这张照片，这个盒子是口译员，它需要，让我给它贴上一个大的标签
I, it takes as input, your program. That you wrote, And, whatever data that you
我，它把你的程序作为输入。那是你写的，而且，不管你写了什么数据
want to run the program on. And it produces the output directly. Meaning that
我想运行这个程序。它直接产生输出。意思是说
it doesn't do any processing of the program before it executes it on the
在上执行程序之前，它不会对程序进行任何处理。
input, So you just write the program, and you invoke the interpreter on the data,
输入，所以您只需编写程序，然后对数据调用解释器，
and the program immediately begins running. And so, we can say that the
程序立即开始运行。所以我们可以说，
interpreter is, is online, meaning it the work that it does is all part of running
解释器是，是在线的，这意味着它所做的工作都是运行的一部分
your program. Now a compiler is structured differently. So, we can draw a picture
你的节目。现在编译器的结构不同了。所以，我们可以画一幅画
here. Which we'll label with a big C, for the compiler, And the compiler takes as
这里。对于编译器，我们将用一个大C来标记它，编译器会将其作为
input just your program. And then it produces an executable. And this
只输入您的程序即可。然后它产生一个可执行文件。还有这个
executable is another program, might be assembly language, it might be bytecode.
可执行文件是另一个程序，可能是汇编语言，也可能是字节码。
It could be in any number of different implementation languages. But now this can
它可以是任意数量的不同实现语言。但现在这个可以
be run separately on your data. And that will produce the output. Okay? And so in
对您的数据单独运行。这将产生输出。好吧?所以在
this structure the compiler is offline, Meaning that we pre-process the program
编译器的此结构处于脱机状态，这意味着我们要对程序进行预处理
first. The compiler is essentially a pre-processing step that produces the
第一。编译器本质上是一个预处理步骤，它生成
executable, and then we can run that same executable on many, many different inputs,
可执行文件，然后我们可以在许多不同输入上运行相同的可执行文件，
on many different data sets without having to recompile or do any other processing of
在许多不同的数据集上，而不必重新编译或执行任何其他处理
the program. I think it's helpful to give a little bit of history about how
这个项目。我认为讲一点历史是很有帮助的
compilers and interpreters were first developed. So the story begins in the
编译器和解释器最先被开发出来。所以故事开始于
1950s and in particular with a machine called the 704 built by IBM. Thi s was
20世纪50年代，特别是IBM制造的名为704的机器。这是他的
their first commercially successful machine, although there had been some
他们的第一台商业上成功的机器，尽管已经有了一些
earlier machines that they had tried out. But anyway the interesting thing about the
他们试用过的早期机器。但不管怎样，有趣的是
704 well, once customers started buying it and using it, is that they found that the
嗯，一旦顾客开始购买并使用它，他们就会发现
software costs exceeded the hardware costs. And not just by a little bit, but
软件成本超过了硬件成本。而且不只是一点点，而是
by a lot And, This is important because these, the hardware in these, those days
很多，这一点很重要，因为这些，这些，那些日子里的硬件
was extremely expensive. And even then when hardware cost the most in absolute
是非常昂贵的。即使在硬件绝对成本最高的情况下
and relative terms, more than they would ever cost again, already the software was
相对而言，比以往任何时候的成本都要高，软件已经
the dominant expense in, in making good use out of computers. And this led a
把计算机用好的主要费用。这导致了一场
number of people to think about how they could do a better job of writing software.
有很多人需要思考如何才能更好地编写软件。
How they could make programming more productive. Where the earliest efforts to
他们如何让编程变得更有效率。在那里最早的努力是
improve the productivity of programming was called speed coding, developed in 1953
提高编程生产率被称为速度编码，开发于1953年
by John Backus. Now, speed coding is what we call today, an early example of an
约翰·巴克斯写的。现在，速度编码就是我们今天所说的，这是一个早期的例子
interpreter. And like all interpreters, it had some advantages and disadvantages. The
口译员。和所有的口译员一样，它也有一些优点和缺点。这个
primary advantage was that it was much faster, to develop the programs. So the,
主要的优点是，开发程序的速度要快得多。所以这个，
in that sense, the programmer was much more productive, But among its
从这个意义上说，程序员的工作效率要高得多，但在它的
disadvantages, code written, speed code programs were ten to twenty times slower.
缺点是，编写的代码、速度编码程序要慢十到二十倍。
Then handwritten programs and that's also true of interpreted programs today. So if
然后是手写程序，今天的解释型程序也是如此。所以如果
you have an implementation that uses an interpreter, they're going to be much
您有一个使用解释器的实现，它们将会很多
slower than either a compiler or writing code by hand. And also, the speed code
比编译器或手工编写代码都慢。还有，速度密码
interpreter took up, 300 bytes of memory. And that doesn't seem like very much. In
口译员占用了300字节的内存。这看起来不是很多。在……里面
fact, 300 bytes, today, would seem like an incredibly tiny, program. But in those
事实上，300字节今天看起来似乎是一个令人难以置信的微小程序。但是在那些
days, you have to keep in mind, that this was 30 Percent Of the memory on the
天，你必须记住，这是30%的内存
machine. So this was 30 percent of the entire memory of the 704. And so the
机器。所以这是704全部内存的30%。因此，
amount of space that the interpreter took up was itself a concern. Now speed coding
口译员占用的空间本身就是一个令人担忧的问题。现在进行快速编码
did not become popular, but John Backus thought it was promising and it gave him
没有变得流行起来，但约翰·巴克斯认为它很有前途，这给了他
the idea for another project. The most important applications in those days were
另一个项目的想法。当时最重要的应用是
scientific computations, and programmers thought in terms of writing down formulas
科学计算，程序员从写下公式的角度思考
in a form that the machine could execute. John thought that the problem with speed
以机器可以执行的形式。约翰认为速度的问题
coding was that the formulas were in fact interpreted and he thought if first the
编码是公式实际上是被解释的，他认为如果第一个
formulas were translated in to a form that the machine could execute directly. That
公式被翻译成机器可以直接执行的形式。那
the code would be faster, And while still allowing the programmer to write the, the,
代码会更快，同时仍然允许程序员编写
the programs at a high level, and thus was the Formula Translation Project or FORTRAN
高水平的程序，因此被称为公式翻译项目或FORTRAN
Project born. Now FORTRAN ran from 1954 To 1957, And interestingly, they thought it
诞生计划。FORTRAN从1954年运行到1957年，有趣的是，他们认为
would only take them one year to build the compiler but it would end up taking three.
他们只需要一年的时间就可以构建编译器，但最终将需要三年的时间。
So just like today, they weren't very good at predicting how long software projects
所以就像今天一样，他们不太擅长预测软件项目有多长时间
would take. But it was a very successful project. By 1958, over 50 percent of all
会花上很长时间。但这是一个非常成功的项目。到1958年，超过50%的
code was written in FORTRAN. So 50 percent of programs were in FORTRAN, And, that is
代码是用FORTRAN编写的。所以50%的程序是用FORTRAN编写的，也就是说
very rapid adoption of a new technology. We would be happy with that kind of
非常迅速地采用了一项新技术。我们会很高兴有这样的一种
success today, and of course at that time they were ecstatic, And everybody thought
今天成功了，当然当时他们欣喜若狂，每个人都认为
that FORTRAN both raised the level of abstraction, improved programmer
FORTRAN既提高了抽象水平，又改进了程序员
productivity, and allowed everyone to make much better use of these machines. So
提高了生产效率，让每个人都能更好地使用这些机器。所以
FORTRAN one was the first successful high level language and it had a huge impact on
Fortran one是第一种成功的高级语言，它对
computer science. In particular, it led to an enormous body of theoretical work. And
计算机科学。特别是，它导致了大量的理论工作。和
one of the interesting things about programming languages, actually, is the
实际上，编程语言的有趣之处之一是
combination of theory. And practice because it's not really possible in
理论的结合。并练习，因为这是不可能的
programming languages to do a good job without having both a, a very good grasp
编程语言要做好，既要有，又要有，掌握得很好
of fairly deep theory and also good engineering skills. So there's a lot of
具有相当深厚的理论知识和良好的工程技能。所以有很多
very good systems building material in programming languages and typically it
非常好的用编程语言构建系统的材料，通常它
involves a very subtle and fruitful interaction with theory. And so, and this
涉及到与理论非常微妙和富有成效的互动。所以，还有这个
is one of the things, I think, that's most attractive about the area's the subject of
是这个地区最吸引人的地方之一，我认为
studying computer science. And the impact of FORTRAN was not just on computer
学习计算机科学。而且FORTRAN的影响不仅仅是在计算机上
science research, of course, but also on the development of, practical compilers.
科学研究，当然，也是关于开发，实用的编译程序。
And, in fact, its influence was so profound, that today, auto compilers still
事实上，它的影响是如此深远，以至于今天，自动编译器仍然
preserve the outlines of FORTRAN one. So what was the structure of FORTRAN one?
保留FORTRAN One的轮廓。那么FORTRAN One的结构是什么呢？
Well it consists five phases lexical analysis and parsing, which together take
它包括五个阶段的词法分析和解析，这五个阶段加在一起
care of the syntactic aspects of the language, semantic analysis, which, of
关注语言的句法方面，语义分析，其中，
course, takes care of more semantic aspects, things like types and scope
当然，它考虑了更多的语义方面，比如类型和范围
rules. Optimization, Which is a collection of transformations on the program to
这是规矩。优化，它是程序上的转换的集合，以
either make it run faster or use less memory. And finally code generation which
要么让它运行得更快，要么使用更少的内存。最后是代码生成，该代码生成
actually does the translation to another generation. And depending on our goals,
实际上是翻译给另一代人。根据我们的目标，
that translation might be to machine codes. It might be to a bite code for a
这个翻译可能是机器代码。它可能是一个比特代码，用于
virtual machine. It might be to another high level programming language. Well
虚拟机。它可能是另一种高级编程语言。井
that's it for this lecture, and next time we'll pick up here and talk about these
这节课就讲到这里，下一次我们将在这里继续讨论这些
five phases in more detail.
五个更详细的阶段。